Dylan Paltra

🗷 dylan.paltra@univie.ac.at | 🖸 dpltr22 | 🔰 @dpaltr22 | 🞓 Dylan Paltra

Personal Profile

My name is Dylan, and I am pursuing a PhD in Political Science at the University of Vienna, Department of Government. My research interests lie in the realm of political representation. I am interested in how politicians communicate representative claims in parliament and social media and how citizens receive these. Specifically, I am interested in the two dimensions of political representation personalization and surrogate representation. On the side of citizens, I am intrigued by the question of what styles of representation they value. To understand these questions, I study legislative speeches of politicians and everything political elites put out online, thereby always trying to use new methods from the field of computational social science.

Education

University of Vienna Vienna, Austria

PhD in Political Science

• Working Title: Me or the party? Investigating the tension between surrogate representation and personalization

· Supervisor: Assoz. Prof. Christopher Wratil

University of Zurich Zurich, Switzerland

MA in Political Science, Minor Methods-Data-Society (Grade: 5.8)

August 2021 - July 2023

• Thesis: The mismatch between citizens perceived bias and actual bias in news coverage (Grade: 6.0) · Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Karsten Donnay

University of Mannheim Mannheim, Germany

BA in Political Science, Minor Public Law (Grade: 1.6)

August 2017 - July 2021

• Thesis: Affective Polarization at German State Elections, 1990 - 2020 (Grade: 1.0)

· Supervisor: Prof. Dr. Rüdiger Schmitt-Beck

Work Experience

ERC Project: "MULTIREP" University of Vienna, Austria

Research Assistant October 2023 -

• PI: Assoz. Prof. Christopher Wratil

- Survey Design (development of questionnaire & experiments)
- Quantiative Text Analysis of Open-Ended Survey Answers

Project: "DigiVox" University of Zurich, Switzerland

Student Research Assistant

- PI: Prof. Dr. Karsten Donnay, Prof. Dr. Eszter Hargittai & Prof. Dr. Lucas Leemann
- · Responsible for constructing First Wave of longitudinal Survey Design • Implementation on Qualtrics
- Supervision of running survey
- Data Wrangling of survey data
- Data Analysis

Project: "Influence of social media on political reporting"

Student Research Assistant

- PI: Dr. Corinna Oschatz & Prof. Dr. Sebastian Stier
- · Building Webcrawler & Parser for different German media outlets
- Building a server-based data base
- · Supervision of technical proceedings

Project: "The Populist Challenge in Parliament"

Student Research Assistant

· PI: Prof. Dr. Jochen Müller

- Responsible for webscraping the wikipedia pages different state parliaments
- · Collecting data on every parliamentarian form 1990 2020
- · Constructing a usable data set for further research

March 2022 - July 2023

October 2024 -

GESIS Cologne, Germany

June 2021 - December 2021

Humboldt University Berlin,

Germany

September 2021 - December 2021

JULY 10, 2024

April 2020 - July 2021

Student Research Assistant

- · PI: Prof. Dr. Christian Stecker
- Responsible for webscraping the different state parliament databases
- Administration and Supervision of an own Database
- Data manipulation

Project: "Experiences of Everyday Racism and Media-Mediated Racism in the (Political) Public Sphere"

MZES Mannheim, Germany

Student Research Assistant

- PI: Prof. Dr. Marius Sältzer
- Helping in designing a Coding scheme for Tweets
- · Helping in developing a semi supervised topic model by building up a dictionary
- · Handcoding of Tweets

November 2020 - February 2021

Publications and Projects

2024 - Oschatz, Corinna; Gil-Lopez, Theresa; **Paltra, Dylan**; Stier, Sebastian; Schultz, Tanjev: *Social media posts as source for political news coverage inside and outside election campaigns: Examining effects on deliberative news media quality.* **Journalism. Online First.** https://doi.org/10.1177/14648849241231698

Work in Progress:

2024 - **Paltra, Dylan**; Sältzer, Marius; Stecker, Christian: Affective States - Cultural and Affective Polarization in a Multilevel-Multiparty System. Under Review.

2024 - **Paltra, Dylan**; Cappellina, Bart; Wratil, Christopher; Fernezelyi, Simon ; Ó Hannracháin, Lóránt: *The Citizens' Concept of Representation: Evidence from an Open-Ended Questions Survey.*

Conferences and Workshops

07/2023 - Summer Institute in Computational Social Science. Summer School, Munich, Germany.

06/2023 - Measuring the mismatch between citizens' perceived and actual bias in news coverage. *EPSA Conference, Glasgow, Scotland.*

04/2023 - Talking about the Weather - Explaining Regional Salience of Climate Change across Time in the German States with Marius Sältzer. *Friedrich-Ebert-Stiftung Workshop, Remote.*

10/2021 - Candidates and Fringe Candidates on Social Media. Digital Democracy Workshop, Zurich, Switzerland.

05/2021 - Affective Polarization Around the World: Measurement, Causes and Consequences. *ECPR Workshop, Remote.*

Skills

Programming R (baseR, RSelenium, seededlda, quanteda), Python (Pandas, NumPy, TensorFlow, Beautiful Soup), SQL, Linux. **Miscellaneous** Shell (Bash), JavaScript, ŁTĘX(Overleaf/R Markdown), Git, Qualtrics, Microsoft Office.

Languages

German Native

English Professional proficiency

Spanish BasicSwedish Basic

JULY 10, 2024 2